hello everyone my name is greg and i
devstuff welcome everyone to episode
4 of the tactics game in unity
in this episode we will cover
pathfinding
before we begin pathfinding
implementation we should clean our root
folder
for clarity's sake this episode is based
on episode 3 and the sister series of
gridmap tutorial this episode will use
majority of the same code and written
script
but flipped to be used on 3d plane
instead of 2d plane
pathfinding or pathing is the plotting
by a computer application
of the shortest route between two points
so let's look at the theory first
here we have
a five by five grid and two points we
want to reach point b
from point a in real life
our brain calculates what we think is
the most efficient route and we follow
it to reach where we want to go most of
the time
you don't even think about this it
happens naturally but computers don't
have that luxury you have to give them a
detailed explanation of how to reach a
certain place
the goal of the a-star algorithm is to
make the process of decision making
computable by a computer
so it will be able to read the map
understands the workable and unvocable
terrain and calculate the shortest path
between point a and b
so our grid map will have cells which
will be our nodes you can walk in all
directions from the node each node will
have three values
g value the working cost from the start
node in our case we will have direct
walking cost 10 and diagonal cost of 14.
hweller or heuristic cost
this is heuristic cost to reach our
final goal this is total cost to reach
the end goal with disregard to stuff
like walls
this value will help us with
prioritizing the notes which are more
likely to lead to the end goal f value
is the total sum of g value and h value
using this value we can prioritize nodes
which is more likely to lead us to the
goal
the algorithm will stop when our endnote
will be found
to make the algorithm work we will have
two lists open list and closed list open
list list of notes ready to be searched
and closed list
a list of nodes which have already been
searched
so we search our environment until we
either reach the end goal or open list
is empty
signifying the fact that we have nowhere
else to search and the target place is
unreachable
so how does it work well a star
calculates the quality of the path and
use the one which seems the most
efficient
first step get all neighbors and
calculate their values
second select the most efficient node we
currently have on our field
third step get all the neighboring nodes
and if they are not in the closed list
already or they are not obstructed by
the wall or impossible terrain
calculate them and add them to the open
list
when you
done with all neighboring nodes add the
calculated node to the closed list
signified by the line under the f value
i will mark these nodes with the line
under the f value
in case the neighbor has been already
calculated before we're re-checking it
for the possibility of newly discovered
route being more efficient
fourth step
repeat this process until we reach point
b
fifth step
when we reach the point trace back to
the point a
and this will be our path
good back to the unity
in the editor create a new script called
pathfinding
add it to grid component
because our pathfinding will always work
with grid map we want to ensure that
this component will always be attached
to the object with grid map
so add the required component grid
good
here we will be describing the
pathfinding process
inside create a new class called path
node
and declare x and y position
then g value h value
and create a property called f-value
which will return the sum of g value and
h value
make a constructor
where we will pass the position of this
node
good then inside pathfinding on the
start
create a new method called init
then store the reference to the grid
create 2g array of pass nodes
to be able to access the with hand
lengths of the grid we need to make them
public
then initialize each node in an array
create a new method called find pass
which will return the path between two
points
in the form of a list of past nodes
and accept four parameters start x and y
and end x and and y
return null immediately
returning no inside find pass will
signify that we haven't found the path
save the reference to the start node and
the end node
create two lists open and close lists
and add the start node to the open list
so now we will be searching through our
grid until we either find the target
node or run out of options
make a while loop with an open list
count more than zero
to keep searching until we run out of
possible nodes
then inside we want to find the node
with the lowest f cost in the open list
create a new variable called current
node and assign the first node from the
open list to this current node
then loop through the list of open nodes
and compare f cost of the current node
against the open list nodes
if one of them is lower than your node
assign it to the current node
besides flatly comparing f costs we want
to prioritize nodes with the lower age
cost so add an additional comparison
of f cost
equals current node f cost and h cost
less than current node h cost
this way if you have a node with equal f
value
but
there is a node with better hvalue we
will use this node instead
remove the selected node from the open
list then add it to the closed list
check if the current node equal to the
target node
if yes that means we found our pass
and let's create and call retrace pass
where we will pass start node and
endnote we will come back to this method
later on when we will be done with our
pathfinding calculations
then we want to get all the neighbors
from the grid by searching 3x3 grid
skip the middle node because it is node
we are currently checking for
we need to check if this neighboring
node is inside the boundaries of the
grid map
to do so we want to introduce an
overload of the check boundary where
instead of using vector 2 ind for
position on grid we will use two
integers
and if it is
we can add this node to the neighbors
list
we want to cycle through this list and
if neighbor is already in the closed
list or it is on the unvocable then we
continue
we don't have a check for unwalkable
node so let's implement it
just return state of possible from the
node
we will expand on walkable and unvocable
system later on
create a new variable movement cost to
neighbor and calculate it using ours
calculate distance plus current node g
value
by getting an absolute value of
difference between node a and node b
then if distance by x is more than
distance by y
returns the distance y multiplied by 14
and distance x minus distance y
multiplied by 10.
otherwise do the same with opposite
values
if our movement calls to neighbor is
less than new node g cost or our
new node is not in the open list
and
if this statement is true
assigns the movement cost
and to the edge velour will be equals to
get distance between this new node and
the endnote
then stores the parent node into the
path node
from which we reach this node
if this note is not present in ours open
list we will add it to the open list
so at this point we are done calculating
nodes for the pass so now we need to
process it
generate a path based on this calculated
values and return this pass
so we will be able to use it for like
our character or anything else
so open the
retrace path
where we will retrace our paths back
using our parent nodes from our space
nodes create new list of nodes called
pass
then create a variable
for current node
assigned end node as a current node
because we will be retracing the path
from the end
while current node is not equals
starting node
pass add current node and current node
is equals current node's parent
then when we have reached the beginning
of our pass and pretty much traced back
our path
we need to reverse
this list
return the generated path from the place
where we detected the completion of the
pathfinding
in case our program got through all the
open lists and did not found the path to
the end node we will return no meaning
there is no path to the desired location
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
so now when we have an ability to
calculate the pass we should be able to
call this method from somewhere
and then use calculated paths to show it
on our screen
open the grid control in grid control we
want to use the pathfinding of the
target grid
we need variable for current position
and 4 pass
then in the update when you click on the
grid you want to use the grid position
and find the path from the current
position to the grid position
store the path from the pathfinding
in the on draw gizmos cycle through all
the path nodes and draw the line
we need to use get world position in the
grid because our paths node have a
position of the node on the grid not in
the world
good
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any ideas about
code please leave your comment below if
you are interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe if you
want to support further you can find my
patreon in the description
special thank you to andrew v long and
this old hajj do
for their generous support
with best regards see in the next
episode
you